Guide to the Rosenberg Family Correspondence rosenberg
Testing import and export
Rosenberg Family Correspondence
1938-2010
1938-1946
Testing import and export
Rosenberg, Alfred
Rosenberg, Alise
Rosenberg, Victor
Rosenberg, Eugen
Rosenberg, Julius
Rosenberg, Johanna
Rosenberg, Nathan
Rosenberg, Emmy
rosenberg
1 Linear Feet 2 manuscript boxes
The 105 letters in this collection document the experience of a German Jewish family in the years immediately before, during, and shortly after World War II. Nathan and Johannna Rosenberg of Breisach, Germany, had three sons: Julius (1900-1942), Eugen (1901-1964), and Alfred (1911-2005). Eugen left for Palestine in 1935. Alfred, with his wife and her parents immigrated to the United States in August 1938. Most of the letters were written to Alfred by his brothers, his parents, and other relatives between 1938 and 1946. Most of the letters are from Julius, Emmy, Nathan, and Johanna; some of these they wrote from the labor camp in Gurs to which many Jews in Breisach were deported in October 1940. Contains typewritten transcriptions (German) and English translations for most letters.
Biographical / Historical
These letters were written by various members of the Rosenberg family, particularly parents Johanna and Nathan; son Julius, b. 1900 (living in Breisach, Germany, and often writing with his fiancee Emmy); son Eugen, b. 1901 (living in Palestine with his wife Lea and a young son); son Alfred, b. 1911 (living in Brooklyn and later Pennsylvania with his wife, Alise, and her parents). The letters were received and collected by Alfred Rosenberg and donated by his son, Victor Rosenberg. In 1940 Julius, Emmy, Nathan, Johanna, and other extended family members from Breisach were deported to a labor camp in Gurs, France. Johanna died while interned there in 1941. The camp was deported to Auschwitz in August 1942, where Julius was murdered. Further information about Emmy, including her family name, is unknown. Nathan survived the war at a hospice in southern France and died there in December 1945.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Victor Rosenberg, 2009.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains one linear foot of material and includes 105 letters between Rosenberg family members, friends, and acquaintances. It documents the firsthand experiences of a German Jewish family before, during, and after the Holocaust, and also includes the experiences of family members who emigrated from Germany in the years immediately before the Second World War. The letters were received and collected by Alfred Rosenberg, and as a result most are addressed to him and Alise Rosenberg and few are written by them.
- "The Power of a Family Archive" by Victor Rosenberg, February 9, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letter from Johanna and Nathan Rosenberg, and Rose Recipient to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg and Wiehler family, August 22, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letter from Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg and Aunt Rosa to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, September 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg and Jakob [Wiehler?], September 16. 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letter from Nathan Rosenberg to Eugen Rosen, September 28, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letter from Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg and Rosel to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, October 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, October 14, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letter from Eugen Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, October 23, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, November 17, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Letter from Eugen Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, December 26, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg, Johanna Rosenberg, and Rosel to Alfred Rosenberg, December 30, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg and Johanna Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, February 20, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, March 7, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg and Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, March 26, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg and Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, April 21, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letter from Eugen Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, May 1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Letter from Eugen Rosenberg to Julius Rosenberg, May 1, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Letter from Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg and Julius Rosenberg, May 12, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Letter from Eugen Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, May 30, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Letter from Henri Raphael and Johanna Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, May 31, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg and Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, May 31, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg and Lea Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, June 8, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg, Emmy, Johanna Rosenberg, and Rosel to Alfred Rosenberg [?], June 28, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Letter from Eugen Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, July 20, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg and Emmy to Alfred Rosenberg, August 22, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg and Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, September 3, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg and Emmy to Alfred Rosenberg, September 13, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg and Emmy to Alfred Rosenberg, October 1, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Letter from Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg to Veis Bloch c/o Gustav Dreyfu&#223, October 1, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, October 8, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, October 13, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Letter from Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg and the Wiehler Family [?], October 22, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg and Emmy to Alfred Rosenberg, October 26, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, November 2, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, November 13, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Letter from Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg and Aunt Rosa to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, November 20, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Letter from Nathan Rosenberg to Gustav and Mrs. Dreyfu&#223, November 26, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Letter from Eugen Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, January 11, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, January 30, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, March 13, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg and Emmy to Alfred Rosenberg, March 24, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Letter from Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, April 21, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, May 3, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg and Emmy to Alfred Rosenberg, May 26, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, June 3, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg and Emmy to Alfred Rosenberg, July 14, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Letter from Eugen Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, July 30, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Letter from Nathan Rosenberger (Uncle Nathan) to Alfred Rosenberg, August 7, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Letter from Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg and Julius Rosenberg to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, September 15, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg, Emmy, Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg, and Rosel to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, October 10, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg, Emmy, Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg [?], October 29, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Letter from Eugen Rosenberg to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, November 26, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg [?], December 30, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Letter from Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg and Julius Rosenberg to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, April 9, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to unknown (in Zurich), April 15, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Letter from Jette Rosenberger to unknown, April 20, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg [?], May 6, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Letter from Johanna Rosenberg, Jette Rosenberger, and Julius Rosenberg to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, May 20, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Letter from Emmy and Johanna Rosenberg to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, May 20, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg, Emmy, Nathan Rosenberg to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, June 21, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Letter from Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg, Julius Rosenberg to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, Jakob [Wiehler?], July 18, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg, Jette Rosenberger to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, Jakob [Wiehler?], July 29, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Letter from Jette Rosenberger, Johanna Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg (?), August 1941 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, August 25, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Letter from Julius Rosenberg, Nathan and Johanna Rosenberg, Jette and Louis Rosenberger to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, Jakob, Frau and Herr Bloch, October 3, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Letter from Gustav and Rosi [Dreyfu&#223?] to Alfred Rosenberg, November 9, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Telegram from "Gustav Dreifus" (Gustav Dreyfuß) to Alfred Rosenberg, November 22, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 67)
- Letter from Nathan Rosenberg and Julius Rosenberg to Gustav Dreyfu&#223, March 26, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Letter from Nathan Rosenberg to unknown, August 13, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 69)
- Letter from Gustav Dreyfuß to Nathan Rosenberg, December 19, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Letter from Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, Frau Bloch to Nathan Rosenberg, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Letter from Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, Frau Bloch to Nathan Rosenberg, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Money order from Egon Blozheimer to [?] Rosenberg, January 10, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Letter from Alfred Rosenberg to Nathan Rosenberg, March 1, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Telegram from Nathan Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, March 4, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Letter from Jules Gros to Alfred Rosenberg, April 22, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Letter from Louis Meinstein to Jules Gros, April 30, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Letter from Louis and Jette Rosenberger to Nathan Rosenberg and Metzger siblings, April 30, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Letter from Alfred Rosenberg to Jules Gros and Nathan Rosenberg, June 13, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Letter from Jette Rosenberger to Alfred Rosenberger [sic], July 3, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Letter from Alfred and Alise Rosenberg to Nathan Rosenberg, July 11, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Letter from Nathan Rosenberg and Jules Gros, July 13, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Letter from Gustav Dreyfuß to Nathan Rosenberg, August 16, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Letter from Nathan Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, September 3, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Letter from Jules Gros to "Herr Rosenberger" (Alfred Rosenberg?), September 4, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Letter from Nathan Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg [?], September 6, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Letter from Alfred and Alise Rosenberg to Nathan Rosenberg, September 26, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Letter from Nathan Rosenberg and Emmanuel Loeb to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg and Frau Bloch, October 14, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Letter from Alfred Rosenberg to Nathan Rosenberg, October 18, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Letter from Gustav Dreyfuß to Nathan Rosenberg, November 12, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Letter from Madame Glichenstein to Nathan Rosenberg, November 22, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Letter from Leopold Baer to Alfred Rosenberg, December 22, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Letter from Leopold Baer to Alfred Rosenberg [?], December 24, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Letter from Louis Rosenberger to Alfred Rosenberg [?], 1946 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Letter from Mr. and Mrs. Siegfried E. Dreifuss to Alfred and Alise Rosenberg, January 6, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Letter from Emmanuel Loeb to Alfred Rosenberg [?], February 10, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Letter from Eugen Rosenberg to Alfred Rosenberg, February 11, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Letter from Jette Rosenberger to Alfred Rosenberg, March 7, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Letter from Emanuel Loeb to Alfred Rosenberg [?], April 19, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Letter from Jette Rosenberger to Alfred Rosenberg, May 7, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Letter from Leopold Baer to Alfred Rosenberg [?], May 21, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Letter from Jette Rosenberger to Alfred Rosenberg [?], June 23, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Letter from Siegfried Loeb and Emanuel Loeb to Alfred Rosenberg [?], August 17, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Letter from Rita Rosenberger, Nathan Rosenberger, René, Aunt Martha to Alfred Rosenberg, August 22, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Letter from Aunt Marie, Fanny to Alfred Rosenberg [?], August 22, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Letter from Jette Rosenberger to Alfred Rosenberg [?], September 12, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Envelopes from Germany and Switzerland censored during World War II to Erna Baum/the Baum siblings, December 5, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Envelopes from Germany and Switzerland censored during World War II to Jack Bloch, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Envelopes from Germany and Switzerland censored during World War II to Alfred Rosenberg, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Clippings Fall 1938 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Clippings Jan. 26, 1941, January 26, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Money Orders, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 44)